ALEX REED:
Hello and welcome
to The Evening Roundup,
your weekly news review.
This week, the Daily Beacon
ran a front-page splash.
The headline read:
Council caught wasting
millions on a mystery scheme.
Strong stuff. But the
council's own report
told a very different story.
The Beacon later admitted:
We may have overstated
the figures in our report.
May have? The whole story
rested on a number
that did not exist.
Over on Channel Nine,
the hosts were just as sure:
This is the biggest scandal
the city has ever seen.
We asked the Beacon
for a comment.
They are yet to respond.
And that is all from us.
Until next week,
thanks for watching.