And now, to the most urgent
of the very many torments
afflicting modern life.
What to do with all the
bloody photos on our phones:
JODY: Piece together
your favourite memories,
literally.
Create your own photo jigsaw
puzzle with PhotobookShop.
Yes, what better way to
cherish those special moments
than turning them
into a jazzy jigsaw
courtesy of the good folk
over at PhotobookShop,
whose customers
are so enthused
with its many products
they’ve taken to the
internet to say so:
SERON CHAU:
I feel like I’m holding a
collectable artbook but
how funny and how surreal
that all the art inside
this book is my own.
Yes, funny and surreal!
And what about all those
inspiring mottos you
might otherwise forget?
PRIYANKA PENDAM:
… I jumped on PhotobookShop
and ordered custom wall art
and look at the transformation
Advertising so good you
couldn’t pay for it.
Except of course, it did,
which one online influencer
Gracie McMahon discovered
when PhotobookShop
tried to enlist her too
with the offer of
free product in return
for one Instagram
Reel and five photos,
plus she might be interested
in a nice little commission
on future sales.
But hold on, what’s this?
Please ensure your
videos do not mention
that the product is free,
or sponsored,
or that PhotobookShop
contacted you to create them
in exchange for products.
Offt, sneaky!
And Gracie was having
none of it,
telling the Australian company
behind PhotobookShop that:
… not disclosing
the partnership/
gifting from a brand
is highly illegal.
Please ensure you fix this …
And for good
measure she grassed.
Prompting an investigation
by the consumer watchdog,
which two weeks ago
slapped the company with
a fine of almost $40,000.
Never before
has a business been held
to account for deceiving
customers via covert online
advertising in this way.
The Australian Competition
and Consumer
Commission identifying
more than 100 occasions
on which PhotobookShop
ordered influencers
to conceal payments
of up to $400
in return for publishing
company-friendly propaganda.
And yet,
just last week we still
found posts like these.
Lucy Hawkins promoting
her redecoration ideas
and Rebecca Connolley
gushing over PhotobookShop’s
seamless service.
Lucy told us she had accepted
a gift from the company,
while Rebecca would
not say either way.
But after our impudent
emails and messages,
both pulled down their posts.
And when we spoke
to “oatcapbabe”
whose name in the real
world is Priyanka Pendam
she agreed:
… the disclosure may not have
been as clear as it
should have been.
Once this was brought
to my attention,
I updated the post …
And to her credit,
indeed she did.
In researching this story
we found dozens of posts
on Instagram alone
plugging PhotobookShop
and reaching a
potential 250,000 users,
the genuine opinions
and the paid
opinions, often utterly
indistinguishable.
Which the company
must have missed
in the clean-up program it
promised it had undertaken
since the ACCC’s
meddling:
… a small number of old
posts were identified …
and have since been
corrected or taken down.
Thank you for
pointing this out.
Glad to be of service, Peter.
A spokesperson for the ACCC
told us it expects
all businesses
to comply with
Australian consumer law,
which:
… applies as much
to the digital world
as it does to bricks
and mortar retailers …
Just two years ago the
ACCC found more than 80
per cent of suspicious
influencer posts
it investigated
were potentially deceiving
their followers in
this shabby way.
Leaving the commission in
the unenviable position
of playing whack-a-mole,
trying to police
a staggering number of
pretenders shilling for brands
and hiding it from
their trusting audience
almost makes you pine for
the dreaded mainstream media.